Finding Aid for Z. T. Gerganoff architectural firm records, 1928-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Z. T. Gerganoff architectural firm records 1928-1977
Z. T. Gerganoff (Firm: Ypsilanti, Mich.)
85812 Bb 2
Architectural drawings of the firm of Z.T. Gerganoff, of Ypsilanti, Michigan, (and predecessor firms of R.S. Gerganoff and S.T. Gerganoff). Drawings and specifications for various area churches, service stations and auto dealerships, the Washtenaw County Building, the Ypsi-Ann Building, and miscellaneous businesses and private residences.
27 oversize folders in 6 drawers
1 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of Z. T. Gerganoff (donor no. 6961 ) and came to the library in August 1983.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
Ralph Stephens Gerganoff graduated from the University of Michigan in 1917 with a bachelor's degree in architecture. After practicing in Wisconsin and Detroit, he opened an office in Ypsilanti around 1925. Over the next 40 years, his firm was responsible for a great proportion of the architectural work in Ypsilanti, including most of the Ypsilanti public school buildings, at least 12 buildings at Eastern Michigan University, Beyer Memorial Hospital, and a number of residences, churches, apartment buildings, and businesses. In Ann Arbor, the firm designed the Washtenaw County Building (1955), the Ypsi-Ann Building (later known as the Wolverine Building), Kingsley Apartments, and other buildings. St. Clement Ohridski Macedono Bulgarian Eastern Orthodox Church in Dearborn is one of the firm's best known projects. Schools, churches, county courthouses, residences, and service stations were among the firm's specialties. An album of the firm's work before 1952 is found in the book Architectural Work and Designs by R.S. Gerganoff, in the printed collection.
After R.S. Gerganoff's death in 1966, Stoyan T. Gerganoff took over the firm. He in turn was succeeded in 1980 by Zdravko T. Gerganoff, R.S. Gerganoff's nephew, who had worked for R.S. Gerganoff during the 1950's and who during the 1960s had opened his own architectural firm.
The Z. T. Gerganoff records represent a small portion of the firms output. In 1983, the firm's offices at 206 N. Washington in Ypsilanti were sold, and its records offered to the Michigan Historical Collections. Many of the records had been scattered or destroyed over the years, due to the firm's need for space and its practice of returning records to clients after the completion of a job.
Of the records remaining in the office in July 1983, the Michigan Historical Collections accessioned architectural drawings and specifications relating to churches, service stations and auto dealerships, the Washtenaw County Building, Washtenaw Country Club clubhouse, and a few other buildings, along with miscellaneous renderings of residences, apartment buildings, and businesses. Left at the office to be destroyed were drawings of other county courthouses and schools. Drawings of many Ypsilanti buildings had been donated to the Ypsilanti Historical Museum, and drawings of Eastern Michigan University buildings had been turned over to the University.
This record group consists of architectural drawings for 56 of Gerganoff's projects and a smaller series of specifications for two projects. The architectural drawings series is composed of three subseries: churches; service stations and auto dealerships; and other buildings. Within each subseries, buildings are arranged by location and then chronologically (by job number), with undated and miscellaneous material at the end.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Architects.; Architecture.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan.; Service stations.; Church architecture.; Bethany Assembly of God Church (Adrian, Mich.); Jehovah's Witnesses East (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Link Garage and Sales Building (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Pentecostal Church of God (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Washtenaw County Building (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Wolverine Building (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Trinity Episcopal Church (Belleville, Mich.); Zion Evangelical Lutheran Church (Chelsea, Mich.); St. Clement Ohridski Church (Dearborn, Mich.); St. Clement Ohridski Church (Detroit, Mich.); Presbyterian Church (Fenton, Mich.); Methodist Church (Manchester, Mich.); Free Methodist Church (Spring Arbor, Mich.); St. John's Evangelical Lutheran Church (Waltz, Mich.); Banks and Stowe Sandwich Shop (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Baptist Tabernacle (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Calvary Baptist Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Church Building for American Baptist Home Mission Society (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Emmanuel Lutheran Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); First Christian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); First Presbyterian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); St. Luke's Episcopal Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Willow Run Baptist Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Washtenaw Country Club.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Z.T. Gerganoff (Firm: Ypsilanti, Mich.)
Contributors:
Gerganoff, Ralph Stevens, d. 1966.; Gerganoff, Stoyan T.; Gerganoff, Zdravko T.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.
- Architectural Drawings
  - Churches (alphabetical by location)
    - Adrian. Bethany Assembly of God Church (Job no. 75-529) 1975, 25 drawings pencil on paper vellum, blue line prints, thermofax prints (Folder 1)
      (Site plans, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, structural and electrical plans, renderings)
    - Ann Arbor. Pentecostal Church of God, Jackson Road (Job No. 717 1950, 6 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 2)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, electrical and heating plan)
    - Ann Arbor. Jehovah's Witnesses Church, Stadium Blvd. (Job No. 893) 1959, 7 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 2)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, and structural plans)
    - Belleville. Trinity Church, Belleville Road 1950 (Job No. 711), 1950, 7 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 2)
      (Plot plans, floor plans, elevations, sections, electrical and heating plans)
    - Chelsea. Zion Lutheran Church (Job No. 679, church house and pastor's residence) 1947-1949, 17 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 2)
      (Plot plans, floor plans, elevations, sections, details)
    - Dearborn. St. Clement Orthodox Church 1964 (Job No. 921), 50 drawings pencil on paper vellum, blue line prints, photographs
      (Plot plans, renderings, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, structural, mechanical, and electrical plans)
      (specification in Box 1)
      - Dearborn. St. Clement Orthodox Church 1964 (Job No. 921) (Folder 3)
      - Dearborn. St. Clement Orthodox Church 1964 (Job No. 921) (Folder 4)
        (continued)
    - Detroit. St. Clement Ohridski (church house) 2930 25th Street, 1947-1948 (Job No. 653), 8 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 5)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, elevations, sections, details)
    - Fenton. Presbyterian Church 1961 (Job No. 902), 10 drawings blue line prints (Folder 5)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, structural, mechanical, and electrical plans)
    - Manchester. Methodist Church (addition) 1958 (No Job No.), 10 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 5)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, and heating plans)
    - Spring Arbor. Spring Arbor Free Methodist Church (addition) 1958 (Job No. 77-546), 50 sheets pencil on paper and paper vellum, blue line prints, thermofax prints (Folder 6)
      (Site plan, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, structural, electrical, and mechanical plans)
    - Waltz. St. John's Evangelical Lutheran Church 1957-1958 (Job No. 862), 22 drawings blue line prints (Folder 6)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, structural and mechanical plans)
    - Ypsilanti. Church Building for American Baptist Home Mission Society, E. Forest Avenue and Allen Street 1943 (Job No. 571), 3 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 8)
      (Floor plans, elevations, sections, details)
    - Ypsilanti. Baptist Tabernacle, 218 E. Forest Avenue 1943 (Job No. 573), 2 drawings (Folder 8)
      (Floor plans, elevations)
    - Ypsilanti. Emmanuel Lutheran Church (proposed parish hall) 1955 (Job No. 638), 4 drawings blue line prints (Folder 8)
      (Floor plans)
    - Ypsilanti. First Presbyterian Church (new organ and choir gallery) 1946 (Job No. 643), 20 drawings pencil on paper and paper vellum (Folder 8)
      (Floor plans, sketches, elevations, sections, perspectives)
    - Ypsilanti. First Presbyterian Church 1950 (Job No. 737), 13 drawings pencil on paper and paper vellum, blue prints (Folder 9)
      (Floor plans, heating plans)
    - Ypsilanti. St. Luke's Church (remodeling) 1951 (Job No. 750), 3 drawings pencil on paper vellum, and specifications (Folder 9)
      (Floor plans, sections, details)
    - Ypsilanti. Calvary Baptist Church (addition), Oakland Boulevard and Davis Street 1952-1955 (Job No. 765), 9 drawings pencil on paper vellum, blue line prints (Folder 9)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, elevations, sections, structural plans)
    - Ypsilanti. Willow Run Baptist Church (addition) 1952 (Job No. 772), 5 drawings pencil on paper vellum, blue line print (Folder 9)
    - Ypsilanti. Emmanuel Lutheran Church (addition) 1952 (Job No. 847), 19 drawings blue line prints (Folder 9)
      (Plot plans, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, structural, and mechanical plans)
    - Orthodox churches (No Job No.), 36 drawings pencil on paper, paperboard, and paper vellum, blueprints, photograph (Folder 10)
      (studies, etc.)
  - Service Stations and Auto Dealerships
    - Ann Arbor. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (gasoline station), S. University at Church Street 1939 (No Job No.), 4 drawings blueprint (Folder 11)
      (Douglas D. Loree, architect)
    - Ann Arbor. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (service station), SW corner of Packard and Stadium Road 1940 (Job No. 515), 5 drawings blueprint, and specifications (Folder 11)
      (Plot plans, floor plans, elevations, section, details)
    - Ann Arbor. Link George and Sales Building, Huron and Division Streets 1947 (Job No. 655), 4 drawings blueprints (Folder 11)
    - Ann Arbor. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (service station), E. Ann and Glen Streets 1950 (Job No. 720), 6 drawings pencil on paper vellum, blue print (Folder 11)
      (Plot plans, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, structural plan)
    - Belleville. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. and Mr. J.L. Patterson (service station), Huron River Drive and Riggs Street 1937, 1942 (Job No. 474), 6 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 11)
    - Dearborn Township. W.J. Cunningham (service station), Van Born and Jim Daly Roads 1945 (No Job No.), 4 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 11)
      (Plot plan, floor plan, elevations, sections, details)
    - Garden City. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (store building and addition), NW corner Ford and Middle Belt Roads 1940 (Job Nos. 514, 517), 6 drawings pencil on paper vellum and blueprint and specification (Folder 11)
      (Plot plans, floor plans, elevations, sections)
    - Milan. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (Ford-Gulf Service Station) 1938 (Job No. 480), 8 drawings pencil on paper and paper vellum (Folder 11)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, rendering, elevations, sections, framing plan)
    - Northville. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (service station), Main and Wing Streets 1941 (Job No. 531), 3 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 12)
    - Wayne. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (Gulf service station) 1938 (Job No. 481), 8 drawings pencil on paper and paper vellum (Folder 12)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, rendering, elevations, sections, details, framing plan)
    - Wayne. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (service station), Wayne and Van Born Roads 1942 (Job No. 558), 5 drawings blueprint, and specification (Folder 12)
    - Wayne County. Vannoy Brothers (garage and service station), Joy Road and Middle Belt Road 1946 (Job No. 626), 10 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 12)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, elevations, sections, structural plan)
    - Wayne Cty. Texaco Station for Peter Theodore, Inc. (Detroit) Metropolitan Wayne County Airport) 1959 (Job No. 895), 14 drawings blue line print (Folder 12)
      (site plans, floor plan, elevations, sections, details, structural, mechanical, and electrical plans)
    - Ypsilanti. George W. Hayes Realty Co. (garage building), Michigan Avenue at Water Street 1928-1929 (Job No. 368), 3 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 13)
    - Ypsilanti. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (oil station and store), Michigan Avenue 1929 (Job No. 374), 10 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 13)
    - Ypsilanti. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (service and oil station), 15 E. Michigan Avenue 1935 (Job No. 432), 7 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 13)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, elevations, sections)
    - Ypsilanti. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co. (store building), 102 E. Michigan Avenue at River Street 1945 (Job No. 591), 5 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 13)
    - Ann Arbor. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co., State Street at Ann Arbor Road 1944 (No Job No.), pencil on paper vellum (Folder 13)
      (Property map)
    - Livonia. D.M. Silkworth Oil Co., Plymouth and Middle Belt Road 1952 (No Job No.), pencil on paper vellum (Folder 13)
    - Chelsea. L.G. Palmer Garage Building; and unidentified building, (No Job No.), 2 items (Folder 13)
      (Renderings)
  - Other Buildings
    - Ann Arbor. Washtenaw County Building, Huron and Main Street 1946 (Job No. 592), 58 drawings pencil on paper and paper vellum, water color on cardboard
      (Plot plans, floor plans, renderings, elevations, sections, details, structural, mechanical, electrical plans)
      (specifications in Box 1)
      - Ann Arbor. Washtenaw County Building, Huron and Main Street 1946 (Job No. 592) (Folder 14)
      - Ann Arbor. Washtenaw County Building, Huron and Main Street 1946 (Job No. 592) (Folder 15)
    - Ann Arbor. Washtenaw County Building, Huron and Main Street 1953 (Job No. 775), 58 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 16)
      (Plot plans, rendering, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, structural, mechanical, electrical, furniture plans)
    - Ann Arbor. Washtenaw County Building, Huron and Main Street 1953 (Job No. 775), 58 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 17)
    - Ann Arbor. Washtenaw County Building (concessions area) 1955 (Job No. 775B), 3 drawings blue line prints (Folder 16)
      (Floor plan, elevations, roughing in, equipment)
    - Ann Arbor. Washtenaw County Building (concessions area) 1955 (Job No. 775B), 3 drawings blue line prints (Folder 17)
    - Ann Arbor. Washtenaw County Building (parking structure) 1955 (Job No. 810), 12 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 18)
      (Plot plan, floor plans, sections, details, mechanical plans)
    - Washtenaw County Building (remodeling) 1966-1967 (Job No. 951), 7 drawings pencil on paper vellum, blue line prints (Folder 18)
      (Floor plans, details, mechanical plans)
    - Washtenaw County Building (annex) 1967 (Job No. 6706), 41 drawings pencil on paper and paper vellum, sepia print, blue line prints, pencil on mylar (Folder 19)
      (Plot plans, floor plans, elevations, sections, details, structural mechanical, electrical plans)
    - Ann Arbor. Ypsi-Ann Building, 4th Avenue and Washington Street (No Job No.), 6 drawings ink on cardboard, photostats, printed flyer (Folder 20)
      (Renderings, floor plans)
    - Ypsilanti. Washtenaw Country Club (clubhouse, garage, and tool house), Packard Road 1929 (Job No. 367), 32 drawings pencil on paper, ink on linen, blue-prints (Folder 21)
      (Studies, site plans, floor plans, renderings, elevations, sections, details, structural, and heating plans)
    - Ypsilanti. D.M. Silkworth (residence), Huron and Race Street 1935 (Job No. 426), 4 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 22)
    - Jeff Silkworth (house) 1942 (Job No. 546), 2 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 22)
    - Ypsilanti. Banks and Stowe (sandwich shop), Michigan Avenue and River Street 1944 (No Job No.), 2 drawings pencil on paper vellum (Folder 22)
      (Plot plan, floor plan, elevations, section)
    - Miscellaneous (apartment buildings) (No Job No.), 7 drawings ink on paper and cardboard, photostats (Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous (businesses) (No Job No.), 8 drawings photostats, pencil and ink on paper and cardboard (Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous (single family residences) (No Job No.), 50 drawings approximate number; pencil and ink on paper and cardboard, water color on cardboard, photostats
      - Miscellaneous (single family residences) (No Job No.) (Folder 25)
      - Miscellaneous (single family residences) (No Job No.) (Folder 26)
      - Miscellaneous (single family residences) (No Job No.) (Folder 27)
- Specifications
  - Washtenaw County Building (Box 1)
  - St. Clement Orthodox Church (Box 1)